<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<mapdata>
  <marker type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Anderson Mound, Indiana" state="Indiana" src="1--Anderson mound.JPG" lat="40.09908414736847" lng="-85.6163477897644"> <![CDATA[This was once a ceremonial center on the eastern edge of White River.  Used for religious rituals from about 250 BC to AD 200, it was built on a high point near creeks and springs.  There are several mounds and embankments or enclosures, including the Great Mound and Circular Earthworks, and the Circle Mound and Rectangular Earthworks. Circle Mound is shown here.  It is contained within the Rectangular Earthworks, which had three enclosures.  The Circle Mound (5 BC-70 AD) was oriented to the sunrise at the equinox, and the enclosure was aligned with the sunrise and sunset at the summer and winter solstice.  This enclosure is 285 feet long, 225 feet wide, 6 feet high, with a gateway at the east end.  The embankment was constructed to allow people to view the rising and setting of the sun, moon, and brighter stars as well as the Pleiades Constellation.  The mound is 148 feet long and 72 feet wide.  The Great Mound is one of eight contained within the Circular Earthworks.  This mound has a 350 feet diameter.  It was a natural mound around which a ditch 60 feet wide and 10 feet deep was constructed.  Over time, people from different communities brought the remains of certain deceased persons (presumably leaders of family groups) to be reburied here.  Pilgrims also came for other kinds of ceremonies, bringing offerings.  There once were hundreds of sites of similar earthworks in Indiana that shared religious symbolism. This mound complex is located in Mounds State Park near Anderson.  Photo courtesy of Archaeological Resources Management Service, Ball State University.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Anderson Mounds" url="http://www.moundsstatepark.org" name2="Mounds State Park" url2="www.in.gov/dnr/parklake/2977.htm"><![CDATA[These two websites provide basic contact and visitor information for the Anderson Mounds at Mounds State Park.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="political">
	<caption name="Angel Mounds, Indiana" state="Indiana" src="2--Angel Mound.JPG" lat="37.947734058200716" lng="-87.46026992797852"> <![CDATA[From 1000-1450 this was a political-ceremonial center, near what is now Evansville in southwest Indiana.  Several thousand people lived in this town, growing corn in the rich bottom land of the Ohio River.  The administrative center was protected by a stockade made of wattle and daub.  Inside was a plaza surrounded by three major platform mounds and eight other mounds.  The elite families lived on top of the platform mounds. The ordinary farmers lived in square houses, the corners of which were oriented to the four cardinal directions.  A temple was on top of one of the large mounds, where elite ceremonial authorities presided over rituals.  This was a regional center ruled by a warrior-noble.  Satellite villages extended out for many miles, and the elites participated in a far-reaching trade network of valuable objects.  The site is named after the landowner, Mathias Angel.  Photo courtesy of Michael Linderman.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Angel Mounds State Historic Site" url="http://www.angelmounds.org" ><![CDATA[The Angel Mounds website provides information on the many programs and events that take place at Angel Mounds, including the annual Native American Days.  The website also offers an extensive photo gallery that depicts the mounds, the interpretive center, and past events.]]></visitor>
</marker>

  <marker type="effigy">
	<caption name="Mendota Bird Effigy Mounds, Wisconsin" state="Wisconsin" src="3-Mendosa effigyb&b.jpg" lat="43.13483061737531" lng="-89.39534425735474"> <![CDATA[These huge bird effigy mounds are on the site where the Mendota State Hospital was built.  The largest bird effigy has a 624-feet wing span and is a little over 3 feet high..  It is the largest existing effigy mound in the Midwest.  Certainly an important gathering place for mortuary activities sometime between 700-1200 AD, the site has three bird, 2 panther (water spirit), 2 bear, one deer, and several conical mounds.  The site is in what was once a food-rich region on Lake Mendota near Madison.  There were at least 800 groups of effigy mounds in eastern and west-central Wisconsin, the heartland of effigy mound culture.  These centers often were associated with sites where conical mounds were constructed much earlier, an indication that the builders of the effigy mounds recognized the sacred character of a place over a long period of time.  Photo courtesy of James B. Stoltman.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Lake Mendota Effigy Mounds
Mendota Mental Health Institute" url="http://dhs.wisconsin.gov/mh_mendota/Mendota/mounds.htm" ><![CDATA[The Lake Mendota Effigy Mounds are on the grounds of the Mendota Mental Health Institute.  Their website provides brief background information, a short bibliography, and contact information.]]></visitor>
</marker>

  <marker type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Mound City, Ohio" state="Ohio" src="4-Mound City.jpg" lat="39.3535" lng="-82.998798"> <![CDATA[Mound City was a ceremonial center used from approximately 1-200 AD, and five to seven hundred years later other peoples used it to bury their dead in already existing mounds.. Today it is three miles northwest of Chillicothe, Ohio and is one of five sites within the Hopewell Culture National Historical Park in Ross County.  The rectangular earthwork encloses 13 acres and contains at least 24 mounds.  The enclosure is about four feet high and has gateways on the east and west.  The largest mound has a diameter of 90 feet and a height of 18 feet.  The mounds covered structures used for burials, and the sacred space within the enclosure probably was used for rituals .  In one of the mounds was a large cache of animal effigy pipes, mostly in the form of birds and land animals, that had been left as offerings, probably by family groups or groups of religious leaders.  While there were other ceremonial centers in Ohio at this time, there also were small communities that apparently lacked interest in the ceremonies held at the centers.  Today the site is managed  by the National Park Service. The name "Hopewell" comes from Mordecai Hopewell, who was the landowner in the 1890s of one the earthwork sites in the Park.  Photo courtesy of Ross County Engineer. ]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Mound City Group
Hopewell Culture National Historical Park" url="http://www.nps.gov/hocu" ><![CDATA[This website administered by the National Park Service provides visiting information as well as historical and cultural background for teachers and students.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="ceremonial">
	 <caption name="Newark Earthworks, Ohio" state="Ohio" src="5-Newark.JPG" lat="40.00278285862698" lng="-82.98662424087524"> <![CDATA[This ceremonial center was occupied, visited, and modified between 1-400 AD.  The largest of the ceremonial centers during this time, it covered more than four square miles and consisted of geometrical earthworks and conical mounds. The Great Circle Earthwork was 5 to 14 feet high with a diameter of 1,200 feet.  It encompassed 30 acres and in the center was a large building with an altar. The Octagon contained 50 acres (large enough to hold four Roman Colosseums), and the Observatory Circle had a diameter of 1,054 feet and contained 20 acres.  From points on the Observatory Circle and Octagon (shown in this photo), the moon could be tracked across the sky throughout its 18.6 year-long cycle.  An ellipse  surrounded numerous conical mounds up to about 20 feet high and these contained burials.  Parallel walls or passageways connected the principle enclosures and the waterways by which many of the pilgrims came to the center.  Parallel walls also stretched toward another ceremonial center some 60 miles to the southwest.  In the center of the complex there was a pond.  Sky, earth, and water symbolism figured importantly in the rituals held inside the enclosures.  The architecture was not haphazard.  Rather, there were geometrical relationships between earthworks. For example, the circumference of the Great Circle equaled the perimeter of the large square enclosure at the site.  All that remains of this remarkable center is the Great Circle, Octagon and Circle, and fragments of the Square.  The embankments have been incorporated into the nearby town of Newark, with the Octagon used as a golf course.  Today the Newark Earthworks is recognized as a National Historic Landmark.  Photo courtesy of Greater Licking County, Convention and Visitors Bureau.  Photo by Timothy E. Black.   ]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Newark Earthworks" url="http://ohsweb.ohiohistory.org/places/c08" ><![CDATA[The Ohio State Historical Society provides limited information on the three major segments of the Newark Earthworks&#8212;Great Circle, Octagon, and Wright Earthworks&#8212;and announces the opening of The Great Circle Earthworks Museum.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Mound Park, Minnesota" state="Minnesota" src="6-MdsParkView.jpg" lat="44.952043477636174" lng="-93.0690050125122"> <![CDATA[These mounds once were part of a group of 18, the largest of which (shown here) was 18 feet high with a diameter of 67 feet.  Between 200 BC and 200 AD, this was a site of burial rituals in which the remains of important people were placed in stone lined crypts.  The Dakota village of Kaposia was near these mounds in the 17th century and they may have interred deceased members of their community there.  At one time there were over 12,500 conical and effigy mounds in Minnesota.  Mound Park is in St. Paul.  Photo courtesy of the Minnesota Office of the State Archaeologist.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Indians Mounds Park, Saint Paul" url="http://www.stpaul.gov/facilities.asp?page=detail&RID=53" ><![CDATA[The Saint Paul municipal website offers contact information and limited background information.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Ogden-Fettie Mound Group, Illinois" state="Illinois" src="8-Ogden.JPG" lat="40.35040350928059" lng="-90.115120410919190"> <![CDATA[This ceremonial center existed 2.000 years ago on a terrace in the floodplain of the Spoon River.  Here there were at least 35 burial mounds distributed in a crescent-shaped pattern.  The mound in the photo was the largest&#8212;175 feet long, 200 feet wide, and 15 feet high.  Amid the mounds was a village, the residents of which conducted burial and other rituals there. The site is one of several ceremonial centers in this part of the Illinois River valley.  The Illinois sites differ from the ceremonial centers in Ohio where most of the ritual participants were pilgrims, not residents, and where participants made astronomical observations.  The Ogden-Fettie site is located between Lewistown and Havana in Fulton County.  Photo courtesy of Illinois State Museum.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Ogden-Fettie Mounds
Dickson Mounds Museum" url="http://www.museum.state.il.us/ismsites/dickson" ><![CDATA[The Dickson Mounds Museum is a branch of the Illinois State Museum. The website provides information on exhibits, programs, events, and tours for teachers, students, and the general public.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="effigy">
	<caption name="Great Serpent Mound, Ohio" state="Ohio" src="9-serpent mound.JPG" lat="39.23757161784571" lng="-83.6114501953125"> <![CDATA[Located in Adams County, this is the largest serpent effigy mound in the world.  It was built by people from a nearby farming village community about 900 years ago and used as a sacred site for over a hundred years.  The earth sculpture is 1,348 feet long from tip to tip. There were burial mounds nearby but the Serpent Mound was a monumental calendar and a place for rituals probably designed to generate life.  The sculpture probably represented the Horned Serpent, a spirit being associated with the underworld.  In molting, the snake is reborn and, in its association with water, is linked to rain and fertility. The coils of the snake were aligned with the summer and winter solstice sunrises and the equinox sunrise, so the sun’s cycle could be tracked here. The head is aligned to the summer solstice sunset.  Photo courtesy of Timothy A. Price and Nichole I.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Serpent Mound State Park" url="http://ohsweb.ohiohistory.org/places/sw16/index.shtml" ><![CDATA[The Ohio State Historical Society provides visiting information and basic background on the archaeology and history of the mound site.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="political">
	<caption name="Cahokia Mounds, Illinois" state="Illinois" src="13-Twins and Monks.JPG" lat="38.6554546466701" lng="-90.0585150718689"> <![CDATA[Cahokia was a major regional center from about 1050-1350 AD.  In 1150, it was larger than London was at that time. Cahokia covered about 6 square miles with 120 mounds, and from 1175-1275, its administrative center was fortified with a defensive stockade built in four stages.  Here the elite lived around the Grand Plaza, where they conducted ceremonies, supervised public works, and probably distributed crops from granaries replenished by Cahokia’s farmers and tribute from surrounding villages.   Outside this administrative center was a residential area largely for non-elites who lived in family compounds.  This photo shows Monks Mound facing the Fox and Round Top Mounds, known as the "Twin Mounds." Monks Mound stood ten stories high and had pole and thatch buildings used by the ruler for various activities.  To the south was the rectangular Fox Mound, 160 feet long, 125 feet wide, and 46 feet high.  It probably was the base for a structure that contained the remains of members of some of the elite, and it was associated with Round Top Mound, which was 44 feet high and which may have been another place for elite burials.  Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site is near Collinsville.  It is a National Historic Landmark and a UNESCO World Heritage Site.  Photo courtesy of Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site. ]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Cahokia Mounds State Historic Site" url="http://www.cahokiamounds.com" ><![CDATA[The Cahokia Mounds website offers a virtual tour of the mound site using interactive maps, photographs, and embedded video as well as information for visitors.  The website also provides information on guided and self-guided tours of the mound site and the interpretive center.  Educators will find useful information on archaeological methods and the history of the Moundbuilders to prepare students for their visit.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker  type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Nicholls Mound, Wisconsin" state="Wisconsin" src="14-NicholsMound.jpg" lat="42.73125255923887" lng="-90.46361446380615"> <![CDATA[Nicholls Mound is near Trempealeau .  It overlooked the Mississippi River floodplain and the Trempealeau Lakes and was the largest in a complex of 26 mounds.  This conical mound was 90 feet wide and 11 feet high.  After about 2,000 years ago, it was used by a family as a ceremonial burial place for roughly fifty years.  It contained a tomb with the remains of important people buried with prestige goods, and an altar and fireplace.  The mound is named after the man who owned the land when the mound was studied.  The people who came here for ceremonies were influenced by the ceremonial centers in Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois, but many others in the region were not attracted to the Trempealeau Mounds.  Photo courtesy of  S. Clyde (66510).]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Nicholls Mound" url="http://www.byways.org/explore/byways/2249/places/15614" ><![CDATA[The National Scenic Byways Program provides limited background information on the Nicholls Mound.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="political">
	<caption name="Aztalan Mounds, Wisconsin" state="Wisconsin" src="15 Aztalan.jpg" lat="43.065002" lng="-88.913906"> <![CDATA[This town was occupied by as many as 500 people between 1050-1250 AD.  Covering 21 acres, Aztalan had a central plaza with 4 mounds oriented to the cardinal directions.  On the southwest, on the highest elevation, was a platform mound where the ruling family resided.  Shown in the photo, the reconstructed mound had two tiers: the base was 185 by 130 feet and the height was 10 feet.  The platform mound on the northwest had a mausoleum for the elite families.  On top of the platform mound on the northeast was a temple and council house with a sacred fire that burned continually.  The “mound” on the southeast was a hill where there was mortuary activity.  The elite residential district was on a high ridge on the western part of town and the homes of the non-elite population were on lower ground next to the river on the east.  At the north end of the plaza was an underground food depot.  The town was surrounded by a stockade with watch towers.  At this historic site, two mounds and the stockade have been reconstructed.  Once there were more than 40 mounds at Aztalan, named for the Aztecs of Mexico who settlers erroneously believed built this site.  Photo courtesy of Robert Birmington.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Aztalan State Park" url="http://www.dnr.state.wi.us/org/LAND/parks/specific/aztalan" ><![CDATA[This Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources website offers visiting and contact information as well as a video produced by Wisconsin Public Television.]]></visitor>
</marker>
  <marker type="ceremonial">
	<caption name="Norton Mounds, Michigan" state="Michigan" src="16-norton.JPG" lat="42.96669224893662" lng="-85.67696571350098"> <![CDATA[The Norton Mound group is about 2,000 years old and was used ritually for almost a thousand years.  There were originally 17 conical mounds in this center, which was closely related to other centers in Illinois.  Native people in the region have viewed it as an important part of their heritage, and the site is a National Historic Landmark.  One of the few mound centers that survived, it is in the Grand Rapids vicinity.  Photo courtesy of Grand Rapids Public Museum.]]></caption>
  <visitor name="Norton Mounds" url="http://www.grmuseum.org/about_us/sites/norton_mounds" ><![CDATA[The Norton Mounds are located on a property owned by the Grand Rapids Public Museum. The museum's website announces the "Norton Mounds Cultural Resource Project," a project for long-term "preservation, education, access and respect for the site." However, until this project is complete, access to the site is restricted.  ]]></visitor>
</marker>
</mapdata>
