<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<markers>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Red Cliff Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians" src="191RedCliff.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.redcliff-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[This group of Ojibwa signed the 1854 Treaty of La Pointe and, in return for land cession, obtained a reservation with the Bad River Band.  The Red Cliff Ojibwa were led by Chief Buffalo, who was allied with Catholic missionaries.  They splint off from the Bad River Ojibwa, who were not Catholics.  In 1856, the President’s executive order created Red Cliff Reservation for them.  The reservation is 1 by 14 miles along the shore of Lake Superior.  The tribe owns over 7,000 acres.  There are about 5,500 members.  They had expended considerable resources on environmental protection and cultural programs.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="46.339905" lng="-91.726235" />
	<pos lat="46.373668" lng="-91.665811" />
	<pos lat="46.364292" lng="-91.630105" />
	<pos lat="46.392417" lng="-91.564187" />
	<pos lat="46.323016" lng="-91.465310" />
	<pos lat="46.244127" lng="-91.531228" />
	<pos lat="46.279829" lng="-91.544961" />
	<pos lat="46.315508" lng="-91.542214" />
	<pos lat="46.353038" lng="-91.586160" />
	<pos lat="46.324893" lng="-91.707009" />
	<img><![CDATA[Schooner Bay estuary, on the reservation.  Here, the tribe is working on enhancing wild rice stands (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC).]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Bad River Band of Lake Superior Chippewa Indians" src="175A-Bad-River.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.badriver.com" > <![CDATA[This band of Ojibwa ceded land at the Treaty of La Pointe in 1854 and, in return, obtained a reservation. After allotment, much of the land was lost. The tribe owns about 42,000 acres. Over 90 percent of the reservation is wilderness that includes wetlands and wild rice. Today, the Bad River Chippewa number about 7,000 and about one-fourth live on the 192-square-mile reservation. Many practice subsistence fishing here and, at the same time, the tribe has established profitable businesses. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="46.171051" lng="-91.408618" />
	<pos lat="46.084287" lng="-91.265796" />
	<pos lat="46.038964" lng="-91.260303" />
	<pos lat="46.042742" lng="-91.353687" />
	<pos lat="45.948203" lng="-91.359180" />
	<pos lat="45.959556" lng="-91.557495" />
	<pos lat="46.130161" lng="-91.534961" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Scene from reservation.  Photo courtesy of Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources.]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
		<caption name="Lac du Flambeau Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="180LacduFlambeau.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.lacduflambeaunation.com" > <![CDATA[This band has lived in this area since 1745 and they retained it as a reservation after agreeing to cede other land in the 1854 Treaty of La Pointe.  After allotment, much of the reservation land was lost.  The tribe owns about 40,000 acres on this 86,600-acre reservation. There are 260 lakes, 65 miles of stream, and 24,000 acres of wetlands on the reservation.  The name “lac du flambeau” derives from the practice of harvesting fish by torchlight. There are about 3,400 members.  The Lac du Flambeau tribe is the largest employer in the county.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.569836" lng="-90.443945" />
	<pos lat="45.582214" lng="-90.651260" />
	<pos lat="45.453390" lng="-90.650273" />
	<pos lat="45.442492" lng="-90.432959" />
			<img><![CDATA[Pokegama Shores, scene on the reservation.  Photo courtesy of Richardsonpilot. ]]></img>
		  </marker>
		
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
	<caption name="Lac Courte Oreilles Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="186LacCourteOreilles.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.lco-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[These Ojibwas were living on the lake shore as early as 1745 and they resisted removal from Wisconsin.  In the winter of 1850-51, they and many other villages were forced to travel to Sandy Lake to get their treaty goods.  As a result, many died, and the public outcry led to their receiving a reservation at the time they ceded land in 1854 at the Treaty of La Pointe.  Allotment resulted in the stripping away of their timber resources and the loss of much of their land.  They have about 6,500 members, 60 percent of whom live in 23 different communities.  The tribe is the largest employer in Sawyer County.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.680709" lng="-92.084277" />
	<pos lat="45.670618" lng="-91.924976" />
	<pos lat="45.577549" lng="-91.933215" />
	<pos lat="45.561373" lng="-91.817859" />
	<pos lat="45.524638" lng="-91.815112" />
	<pos lat="45.527638" lng="-91.889270" />
	<pos lat="45.495265" lng="-91.892017" />
	<pos lat="45.499605" lng="-92.023853" />
	<pos lat="45.466533" lng="-92.026599" />
	<pos lat="45.470365" lng="-92.134702" />
	<pos lat="45.556578" lng="-92.137449" />
	<pos lat="45.556667" lng="-92.087024" />
	<img><![CDATA[Wild rice beds on the reservation .  Photo courtesy of GLIFWC. ]]></img>
	</marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
	<caption name="St. Croix Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="187StCroix.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.stcciw.com" > <![CDATA[This village lived in the Rice Lake area, and, they apparently did not attend the council at the Treaty of 1854, so did not receive a reservation. They lived on other reservations or inconspicuously in the wider community until the time of the Indian Reorganization Act. Then, they received 1,700 acres scattered throughout the area. Some of this was subsequently sold. Today they have about 5,000 acres (3,000 of which is forest), and the more than 1,000 members live in 11 communities in 4 counties. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.435616" lng="-93.076044" />
	<pos lat="45.436571" lng="-93.018365" />
	<pos lat="45.405045" lng="-93.018365" />
	<pos lat="45.406001" lng="-93.076044" />
	<img><![CDATA[Spring Lake, on the reservation. Here, the tribe has a reseeding project for wild rice (Photo courtesy of GLIWFC).]]></img>
	 </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
	<caption name="Sokaogon (Mole Lake) Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="254rice_lake.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.sokaogonchippewa.com" > <![CDATA[The homeland of this group of Ojibwa was the Rice Lake area.  They apparently were not at the La Pointe Treaty of 1854, and the other Ojibwa groups did not feel authorized to represent them, so they were not party to the treaty and did not receive a reservation.  At the time they accepted the Indian Reorganization Act, the United States recognized them as a tribe and assigned them a 1,700-acre reservation.  Their right to hunt and fish and harvest rice off the reservation also was acknowledged.  The Mole Lake reservation is 12 square miles, largely wilderness and encompassing Rice Lake, Mole Lake, and Bishop Lake.  They obtained more land in 1968 and now the tribe owns about 5,000 acres, some of it off the reservation.  There are about 1,500 members of the Sokaogon Band, about 500 on the reservation.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.089919" lng="-89.653052" />
	<pos lat="45.082216" lng="-89.566709" />
	<pos lat="45.035980" lng="-89.562202" />
	<pos lat="45.043689" lng="-89.658545" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Scene on reservation.  Photo courtesy of U. S. Fish and Wildlife Service. ]]></img>
	</marker>

	<marker type="Potawatomi">
	<caption name="Forest County Potawatomi  " src="188ForestCountyPot.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.fcpotawatomi.com" > <![CDATA[At the Treaty of Chicago in 1833, the Potawatomi ceded their land east of the Mississippi, but many continued to live in Wisconsin.  Because of the 1862 Sioux Uprising, they moved into Forest County, a more remote northern part of the state. Lutheran missionaries at Wittenberg helped some get homesteads in the 1880s but most of this land was lost.  In 1913, the federal government recognized them as a tribe and assigned them a 14,500-acre reservation.  Now the tribe owns about 12,000 acres, which have been in trust status since the 1980s.  The tribe has over 2,000 members, about half of whom live on the reservation.  The tribe’s business income helps strengthen the Potawatomi community.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.074575" lng="-89.241064" />
	<pos lat="45.068420" lng="-89.148804" />
	<pos lat="44.970661" lng="-89.204297" />
	<pos lat="44.962956" lng="-89.346558" />
	<img><![CDATA[Scene on the reservation. Photo courtesy of GLIFWC. ]]></img>
  </marker>
  
<marker type="Potawatomi" duplicate="yes">
	<caption name="Forest County Potawatomi" src="188ForestCountyPot.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.fcpotawatomi.com" > <![CDATA[At the Treaty of Chicago in 1833, the Potawatomi ceded their land east of the Mississippi, but many continued to live in Wisconsin. Because of the 1862 Sioux Uprising, they moved into Forest County, a more remote northern part of the state. Lutheran missionaries at Wittenberg helped some get homesteads n the 1880s but most of this land was lost. In 1913, the federal government recognized them as a tribe and assigned them a 14,500-acre reservation. Now the tribe owns about 12,000 acres, which have been in trust status since the 1980s. The tribe has over 2,000 members, about half of whom live on the reservation. The tribe’s business income helps strengthen the Popawatomi community.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.046580" lng="-89.024585" />
	<pos lat="45.042726" lng="-88.914722" />
	<pos lat="44.992600" lng="-88.909229" />
	<pos lat="44.992600" lng="-89.024585" />
	<img><![CDATA[Scene on the reservation (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC). ]]></img>
  </marker>
  
  <marker type="Potawatomi" duplicate="yes">
	<caption name="Forest County Potawatomi " src="188ForestCountyPot.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.fcpotawatomi.com" > <![CDATA[At the Treaty of Chicago in 1833, the Potawatomi ceded their land east of the Mississippi, but many continued to live in Wisconsin. Because of the 1862 Sioux Uprising, they moved into Forest County, a more remote northern part of the state. Lutheran missionaries at Wittenberg helped some get homesteads n the 1880s but most of this land was lost. In 1913, the federal government recognized them as a tribe and assigned them a 14,500-acre reservation. Now the tribe owns about 12,000 acres, which have been in trust status since the 1980s. The tribe has over 2,000 members, about half of whom live on the reservation. The tribe’s business income helps strengthen the Popawatomi community.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.988742" lng="-88.8976270" />
	<pos lat="44.991667" lng="-88.813098" />
	<pos lat="44.958868" lng="-88.810352" />
	<pos lat="44.958868" lng="-88.870776" />
	<img><![CDATA[Scene on the reservation (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC). ]]></img>
  </marker>
  
   <marker type="Potawatomi" duplicate="yes">
	<caption name="Forest County Potawatomi" src="188ForestCountyPot.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.fcpotawatomi.com" > <![CDATA[At the Treaty of Chicago in 1833, the Potawatomi ceded their land east of the Mississippi, but many continued to live in Wisconsin. Because of the 1862 Sioux Uprising, they moved into Forest County, a more remote northern part of the state. Lutheran missionaries at Wittenberg helped some get homesteads n the 1880s but most of this land was lost. In 1913, the federal government recognized them as a tribe and assigned them a 14,500-acre reservation. Now the tribe owns about 12,000 acres, which have been in trust status since the 1980s. The tribe has over 2,000 members, about half of whom live on the reservation. The tribe’s business income helps strengthen the Popawatomi community.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.939566" lng="-89.031702" />
	<pos lat="44.941496" lng="-88.924585" />
	<pos lat="44.891281" lng="-88.921838" />
	<pos lat="44.893213" lng="-89.023462" />
	<img><![CDATA[Scene on the reservation (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC). ]]></img>
  </marker>
  
	<marker type="Other">
	<caption name="Oneida Tribe of Indians of Wisconsin" src="144SealOneida.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0x000000" url="http://www.oneidanation.org" > <![CDATA[The seal expresses Oneida culture history and values: the eagle represents the need for vigilance; the wampum belt symbolizes the tribe’s connection to the Iroquois Confederacy; the tree of peace figures in the Oneida origin story and displays the clan symbols, wolf, turtle, and bear. 
	In 1820, the Oneida lived in New York and were part of the Iroquois Confederacy. A group of Christian Oneida decided to move to Wisconsin and began moving there in the 1820s, joined by others into the 1880s. They bought land in the Menominee homeland. In 1841, when they were allotted, they had about 65,000 acres. By 1892, much of the land was lost to taxes. They formed an Indian Reorganization Act government in 1934. Today, their enrolled population is about 15,000, and they have about 2,600 acres. The tribe has an active program of community development. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.250085" lng="-88.685010" />
	<pos lat="44.177070" lng="-88.565283" />
	<pos lat="44.072343" lng="-88.723462" />
	<pos lat="44.151159" lng="-88.824736" />
	<img><![CDATA[Tribal seal.  Courtesy of Oneida Indian Tribe of Wisconsin.]]></img>
	</marker>
	
	<marker type="Other">
		<caption name="Menominee Tribe" src="155MennLogo.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0x000000" url="http://www.menominee-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[In 1854 the Menominee ceded land and retained a reservation on a portion of their ancestral territory.  The reservation was 234,000 acres, 95 percent of which was forest.  In 1961 Congress “terminated” the tribe and the reservation became Menominee county, with the land in fee status.  Land subsequently was lost, but Congress restored the Menominee as a federally recognized tribe in 1973 and the reservation status of their land was reestablished.  The Menominee have used much of their business income to buy back land.  Now they have 230,000 acres, mostly owned by the tribe.  The Menominee Tribe has about 8,400 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.817986" lng="-89.841807" />
	<pos lat="44.717986" lng="-88.978818" />
	<pos lat="44.405624" lng="-88.982764" />
	<pos lat="44.455624" lng="-89.478271" />
	<pos lat="44.561622" lng="-89.478271" />
	<pos lat="44.599400" lng="-89.851807" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Scene on the reservation. Photo courtesy of College of Menominee Nation. ]]></img>
	</marker>
	
	<marker type="Other">
  <caption name="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribe " src="190StockbridgeMunsee.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0x000000" url="http://www.mohican-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[The Mohican Christian town of New Stockbridge was experiencing pressure from Americans in 1818, so they began to sell their land and move to Wisconsin in 1821, buying land from the Menominee and Winnebago and hoping to find freedom to live as they wished.  Other Mohicans continued to sell land in New York and move west in the 1820s and beyond.  In 1836 they bought 44,000 acres from the Menominee and a reservation was established for them in 1856 on the southern end of the Menominee Reservation.  In 1871 the size of the reservation was reduced to 11,520 acres and it was allotted.  By 1934, they were largely landless but organized under the Indian Reorganization Act and acquired 3,400 acres.  By 1980, their land base had increased to almost 12,000 acres.  The tribe has about 1,700 members.   ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.571580" lng="-89.543779" />
	<pos lat="44.591003" lng="-89.798271" />
	<pos lat="44.477194" lng="-89.798271" />
	<pos lat="44.470194" lng="-89.608271" />
	<pos lat="44.500194" lng="-89.608271" />
	<pos lat="44.500005" lng="-89.552793" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Scene on the reservation, where the tribe is enhancing the habitat for bald eagles and osprey. Photo courtesy of GLIFWC. ]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Other">
	<caption name="Ho-Chunk Nation of Wisconsin" src="189HoChunk.jpg" state="Wisconsin" color="0x000000" url="http://www.ho-chunknation.com" > <![CDATA[ In 1837 the Ho-Chunk (at the time, Winnebago) were forced to cede their land in Wisconsin, although many remained after the “treaty Winnebago” moved to Minnesota.  In 1859 Congress recognized them as a tribe and agreed to their having a 9 square mile reservation. The Sioux Uprising of 1862 weakened their position, but by 1875 some had received homesteads scattered over 14 counties.  There were a few small settlements on tribal land near Black River Falls and 5 other places.  Still, they had an established presence in Wisconsin in the late 19th century.  By the 1930s, half of the land had been lost to taxes.  They tried to organize under the Indian Reorganization Act, but federal officials rebuffed them.  The formed a government anyway and kept struggling.  In 1963 they adopted a constitution and started acquiring land at Black River Falls, Wisconsin Dells, Tomah, Wisconsin Rapids, and Wittenberg.  In 1994 they changed their official name to Ho-Chunk.  Today they have more than 6,800 acres in trust status, scattered through several counties.  The tribe has about 6,500 members. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="43.960659" lng="-91.381152" />
	<pos lat="43.968518" lng="-91.210864" />
	<pos lat="44.067756" lng="-91.210864" />
	<pos lat="44.071689" lng="-91.359180" />
	<img> <![CDATA[White Otter Site, where the tribe is working to convert the land back to a wetland system. Photo courtesy of GLIFWC. ]]></img>
	</marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa" duplicate="yes">
  <caption name="Red Lake Nation " src="185RedLake.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.redlakenation.com"> <![CDATA[This group of Ojibwa managed to remain in their homeland and to avoid losing any of their reservation lands.  The ceded land in 1863 and 1902 but retained the diminished portion in common.  The leaders refused to allow the reservation to be allotted, thus retaining their land base for future generations.  This reservation contains about 750,000 acres and there are scattered land holdings elsewhere.  The Red Lake is the largest fresh water lake in any state.  It is considered sacred by the Red Lake Ojibwa.  They have an elected council but also an advisory group of chiefs who are descendents of the chiefs who managed to hold the land base for the tribe.  Today, English is a second language.  The tribe has about 10,000 members.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="48.676949" lng="-95.752588" />
	<pos lat="48.651907" lng="-95.576807" />
	<pos lat="48.501388" lng="-95.549341" />
	<pos lat="48.451113" lng="-95.752588" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Good Lake, on the reservation.  Here, the fauna is enhanced to attract waterfowl, which are hunted (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC).  ]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Red Lake Nation   " src="185RedLake.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.redlakenation.com"> <![CDATA[This group of Ojibwa managed to remain in their homeland and to avoid losing any of their reservation lands. The ceded land in 1863 and 1902 but retained the diminished portion in common. The leaders refused to allow the reservation to be allotted, thus retaining their land base for future generations. This reservation contains about 750,000 acres. The Red Lake is the largest fresh water lake in any state. It is considered sacred by the Red Lake Ojibwa. They have an elected council but also an advisory group of chiefs who are descendents of the chiefs who managed to hold the land base for the tribe. Today, English is a second language. The tribe has about 10,000 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.792811" lng="-96.343604" />
	<pos lat="47.698781" lng="-95.332861" />
	<pos lat="47.437478" lng="-95.368779" />
	<pos lat="47.465222" lng="-96.057959" />
	<pos lat="47.596283" lng="-96.332617" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Good Lake, on the reservation. Here, the fauna is enhanced to attract waterfowl, which are hunted (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC).]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
	<caption name="White Earth Reservation" src="tba.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.whiteearth.com" > <![CDATA[The Treaty of 1867 established a reservation for one band of Chippewa and subsequently the federal government tried to bring other bands there to consolidate the Ojibwa on one reservation.  This was resisted by most, but some bands did move to White Earth.  This reservation was allotted, that is, small parcels of land were assigned to individuals and the remainder opened to settlement.  In the early 20th century, through fraud most of the Indian-owned land was transferred to non-Indian ownership.  In 1986 Congress acknowledged wrong-doing as awarded White Earth 10,000 acres and six million dollars in return for the theft of 100,000 acres.  The tribe used this money to start businesses.  Today, the reservation is about 850,000 acres; the tribe owns a little over 70,000 acres.  In fact, the land on the reservation is about 90 percent non-Indian owned.  There are over 20,000 members of the tribe, which contributes to a K-12 school and a tribal college.  Land recovery efforts are underway.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.251212" lng="-96.808398" />
	<pos lat="47.148614" lng="-95.962451" />
	<pos lat="46.713006" lng="-95.917383" />
	<pos lat="46.777958" lng="-96.808398" />
	<img> <![CDATA[]]></img>
	</marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Leech Lake Band of Ojibwe" src="178LeechLakeBandofOjibwe.jpg" state="Minnesota" url="http://www.llojibwe.com" color="0xff0000" > <![CDATA[The colors red, white, yellow, and black represent the oneness and continuity of life. At the center of the seal are the scales of justice.  The mortarboard and diploma represent education.  The soaring eagle and pine trees symbolize the people’s connection with the natural world. The sacred pipe and two eagle features represent the continuity between the Ojibwa people and their ancestors.  The triangle is the wigwam and also stands for the reservation as the people’s home.  (Photo courtesy of Leech Lake Band of Ojibwe).
   Two bands ceded land in 1855 in return for a reservation encompassing Leech Lake, which was expanded and consolidated in the area of three large lakes in 1864.  Boundaries were changed in the late 1860s and early 1870s.  This large reservation contains almost 700,000 acres (212,000 acres actually are lakes).  But the federal government appropriated almost half as the National Chippewa Forest.  There are 40 wild rice producing lakes here, and the tribe is the largest employer in the county.  The tribe contributes to the tribal college and to a tribally-operated K-12 school.  About 9,000 people are enrolled at Leech Lake.  
]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.352376" lng="-94.768188" />
	<pos lat="47.320376" lng="-94.493530" />
	<pos lat="47.215284" lng="-94.510010" />
	<pos lat="47.211574" lng="-94.411133" />
	<pos lat="47.018283" lng="-94.416626" />
	<pos lat="47.014559" lng="-94.334229" />
	<pos lat="46.940022" lng="-94.328735" />
	<pos lat="46.947480" lng="-94.455078" />
	<pos lat="46.995934" lng="-94.427612" />
	<pos lat="47.025730" lng="-94.504517" />
	<pos lat="46.928832" lng="-94.570435" />
	<pos lat="46.951209" lng="-94.713257" />
	<pos lat="46.913909" lng="-94.784668" />
	<pos lat="46.884050" lng="-94.740723" />
	<pos lat="46.814050" lng="-94.603394" />
	<pos lat="46.663323" lng="-94.663818" />
	<pos lat="46.745735" lng="-95.064819" />
	<pos lat="46.884050" lng="-95.136230" />
	<pos lat="46.962394" lng="-95.229614" />
	<pos lat="47.268664" lng="-95.229614" />
	<pos lat="47.240905" lng="-94.779175" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Tribal Seal.]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Bois Forte Band, Minnesota Chippewa Tribe" src="tba.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.boisforte.com" > <![CDATA[The Bois Forte (“dense forest”) band of Chippewa ceded land in the 1854 treaty in return for a reservation in the Lake Vermilian area and hunting/fishing rights in their homeland.  In 1866, they ceded this land in return for sections in the Nett Lake and Deer Creek areas, but in 1881 they obtained Lake Vermilion lands by executive order.  At least half of the reservation land is a wetland, where wild rice grows in abundance. Tribal acreage is located in three areas. Through their business activity, they contribute substantially to the local and regional economy.  The tribe has about 3,200 members.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.602179" lng="-94.060693" />
	<pos lat="47.570179" lng="-93.696172" />
	<pos lat="47.415182" lng="-93.705186" />
	<pos lat="47.462574" lng="-94.071680" />
	<img> <![CDATA[]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa" duplicate="yes">
  <caption name="Bois Forte Band, Minnesota Chippewa Tribe  " src="tba.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.boisforte.com" > <![CDATA[The Bois Forte ("dense forest") band of Chippewa ceded land in the 1854 treaty in return for a reservation in the Lake Vermilian area and hunting/fishing rights in their homeland. In 1866, they ceded this land in return for sections in the Nett Lake and Deer Creek areas, but in 1881 they obtained Lake Vermilion lands by executive order. At least half of the reservation land is a wetland, where wild rice grows in abundance. Through their business activity, they contribute substantially to the local and regional economy. The tribe has about 3,200 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.401795" lng="-94.338477" />
	<pos lat="47.401795" lng="-94.201147" />
	<pos lat="47.328804" lng="-94.201147" />
	<pos lat="47.336108" lng="-94.343970" />
	<img> <![CDATA[]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
	<caption name="Grand Portage Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="183GrandPortage.jpg" url="http://www.grandportage.com" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000"> <![CDATA[The Grand Portage Band of Lake Superior Chippewa long has occupied an area that was instrumental to the fur trade.   In 1854 they ceded land and accepted a reservation that encompassed their main village.  They still work as commercial fishermen and loggers, as they did in the 19th century.  There are about 1,300 members of this tribe.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="47.210015" lng="-90.789014" />
	<pos lat="47.180607" lng="-90.382520" />
	<pos lat="47.003808" lng="-90.767041" />
	<img> <![CDATA[SwampLake, on the reservation.  Rice is harvested here (Photo courtesy of GLIFWC).  ]]></img>
	</marker>

	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Fond du Lac Band, Minnesota Chippewa Tribe" src="143Afonddulac.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.fdlrez.com"> <![CDATA[The outer circular design represents everything in nature (that is, the circle of life), as well as a shield (symbolic of the people’s historic struggle).  The four sections of the inner circle represent the four winds or directions: white (north), red (east), yellow (south), black (west).  The blue/green band between the circles stands for the Mide’wiwin or Medicine Society.  In the center of the arrowhead (which represents the 100-year war the Ojibwa fought with the Dakota and Fox) is a map of the reservation showing the three districts.  The four eagle feathers symbolize prayer and the two hair-ties are Mother Earth and Father Sky.  The reservation map is inserted in a figure eight.  This represents the “Eighth Fire” or the future for which the people are working.  Photo courtesy of Fond du Lac Reservation.
    This band of Lake Superior Chippewa ceded land in the La Pointe Treaty of 1854 in return for a reservation in their homeland.  The tribe is the second largest employer in the county.  They commit significant financial resources to environmental protection, schools, a tribal college, a newspaper, and a museum.  The tribe has about 4,200 members.  
]]></caption>
	<pos lat="46.495762" lng="-93.408145" />
	<pos lat="46.455762" lng="-93.212637" />
	<pos lat="46.328129" lng="-93.126855" />
	<pos lat="46.254966" lng="-93.126855" />
	<pos lat="46.285122" lng="-93.407158" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Tribal Seal, designed by LeRoy De Foe. ]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Mille Lacs Band of Ojibwe" src="177MilleLacs.jpg" state="Minnesota" url="http://www.millelacsojibwe.com" color="0xff0000" > <![CDATA[The Mill Lacs Band struggled historically to remain in their homeland because the policy of the federal government was to remove them to another Ojibwa reservation after they and other tribes ceded land in 1855.  In 1863, they persuaded the United States to allow them to remain in their homeland.  Today their reservation is about 60,000 acres on the shoreline of the lake and on three islands.  They have about 4,000 members, half of whom live on the reservation.  The tribe contributes millions of dollars to charity and gives major support to the local economy.  Among the tribal projects are a museum, two charter schools, an elders’ assisted living center, and a tribal college.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.967404" lng="-94.450708" />
	<pos lat="45.959795" lng="-94.340845" />
	<pos lat="45.914118" lng="-94.346338" />
	<pos lat="45.906502" lng="-94.450708" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Aerial photo of the reservation.  Photo by Aaron Landry.]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Dakota">
  <caption name="Upper Sioux Community, Minnesota" src="184AUpperSioux.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0x003366" url="http://www.uppersiouxcommunity-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[After the 1851 treaty with the Dakota was nullified by the United States, most Dakota were removed west, but a few families remained in the area.  In 1886 they received allotments and later others returned and bought land.  A reservation was established in 1938 and 746 acres was put in trust for the tribe.  The tribe added land to their reservation in 1995.  Today, they have a 1,500-acre reservation and about 500 members. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.288593" lng="-96.757959" />
	<pos lat="45.284694" lng="-96.609644" />
	<pos lat="45.202761" lng="-96.598657" />
	<pos lat="45.206665" lng="-96.703452" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Tribal Seal. The circular design represents the oneness and continuity of life and the four quadrants represent the four directions.  Photo courtesy of the Upper Sioux Community. ]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Dakota">
  <caption name="Lower Sioux Indian Community in the State of Minnesota" src="176ALowerSioux.jpg" state="Minnesota" url="http://www.lowersioux.com" color="0x003366"> <![CDATA[The Mdewakantan band of Dakota ceded land in 1851 in return for reservations in their homeland, but the treaty was nullified by the United States after the 1862 Sioux Uprising.  Several families not involved in the fighting received allotments in the area, but most were removed west.  Over time other families joined the Minnesota community and in 1886 a reservation was established and more land purchased.  Today, the tribe has a 2,000-acre reservation and about 1,000 members, half of whom live on the reservation.  With income from its businesses, the tribe supports many charities and provides health insurance and other services to its members. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.952770" lng="-96.145471" />
	<pos lat="44.950813" lng="-96.002649" />
	<pos lat="44.868549" lng="-96.010889" />
	<pos lat="44.874428" lng="-96.142725" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Scene on reservation: Minnesota River Valley.  Photo courtesy of Lower Sioux Indian Community. ]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Dakota">
  <caption name="Shakopee Mdewakonton Sioux Indian Community" src="177AShakopee.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0x003366" url="http://www.shakopeedakota.org" > <![CDATA[After the 1851 treaty with the Dakota was nullified by the United States, most Dakota were removed west, but families under the leadership of Chief Sakpe received a 250-acre reservation in the 1880s. In 1969, this group separated from the Lower Sioux reservation community and obtained federal recognition as a tribe.  Today the Shakopee-Mdewakanton owns 2,800 acres and has a membership of about 400.  From its income, the tribe makes substantial donations to charily and is a major employer in the county.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.761656" lng="-94.158569" />
	<pos lat="44.762630" lng="-94.054624" />
	<pos lat="44.697299" lng="-94.055997" />
	<pos lat="44.697299" lng="-94.155136" />
	<img> <![CDATA[A Scene on community land.  Photo courtesy of GLIFWC.  ]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Dakota">
  <caption name="Prarie Island Indian Community" src="184PrairieIsland.jpg" state="Minnesota" color="0x003366" url="http://www.prairieisland.org"> <![CDATA[Prairie Island Indian Community.  Members of Chief Red Wing’s band of Mdewakantan Dakota ceded land in 1851 in return for a small reservation in their homeland.  Most Dakota were removed from Minnesota after the Sioux Uprising in 1862 but in 1886 a small group living on Prairie Island was recognized by the federal government and their reservation was reestablished there.  They obtained more land in the 1930s, but shortly afterwards their land was flooded by a dam.  In 2006 the federal government added 1,290 acres to their 2,500-acre reservation in compensation for the flooding.  Tribal acreage is noncontiguous. The tribe has about 750 members, half of whom live on the reservation.  Today, the tribe is the largest employer in the county.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.712661" lng="-93.470865" />
	<pos lat="44.717523" lng="-93.398767" />
	<pos lat="44.676666" lng="-93.300140" />
	<pos lat="44.674719" lng="-93.400178" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Restored native prairie grass, on the reservation (photo courtesy of GLIFWC).  ]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
 	<caption name="Keweenaw Bay Indian Community" src="182KeweenawBay.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.kbic-nsn.gov" > <![CDATA[This band of Chippewa from the Lake Superior was one of the four tribes to sign the Treaty of 1854.  For land cessions, they obtained the L’Anse Reservation in their homeland.  Today, this land base is 92 square miles surrounding the Keweenaw Bay peninsula. Tribally-owned land is scattered amidst non-Indian owned land. The community has almost 3,500 members.  Their businesses support many projects, including a community college. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="46.150721" lng="-89.293750" />
	<pos lat="46.145737" lng="-88.9488379" />
	<pos lat="45.974794" lng="-88.949365" />
	<pos lat="45.974794" lng="-89.161914" />
	<pos lat="46.083574" lng="-89.169941" />
	<pos lat="46.085574" lng="-89.294736" />
	<img><![CDATA[Scene from reservation.  Photo courtesy of GLIFWC.]]></img>
	</marker>

  <marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Lac Vieux Desert Band of Lake Superior Chippewa" src="145SealLacVieux.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.lvdtribal.com"> <![CDATA[This group was on the L’Anse Reservation, then returned to their historic home on the southern shore of the lake and several islands.  They pooled their money and bought land there.  In 1960, they began organizing to obtain recognition as a separate band (or tribe).  In 1988, the community received federal recognition as a separate tribe.  Today, they have about 1,300 acres.  There are about 600 members. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.659821" lng="-89.889136" />
	<pos lat="45.659821" lng="-89.757861" />
	<pos lat="45.7016554" lng="-89.757861" />
	<pos lat="45.706554" lng="-89.889136" />
	<img><![CDATA[Tribal Seal.  The seal that appears on the flag was designed in 1988 at the time the tribe received federal recognition.  Giiwegiizhigookway Martin, in consultation with her mother Rose Polar Martin, created the design.  The four sections represent the four seasons, and the four colors in each section represent the four directions.  The four original clans are symbolized by the eagle, bear, turtle, and fish.  Floral designs represent the artistic heritage of the Ojibwas, and the wild rice in the lower right quadrant shows the importance of traditional subsistence in Ojibwa life today.  The drum design in the center represents the life force, and the community’s term for their reservation in the native language is written there: “Old Planting Ground” (the original homeland).  Photo courtesy of Lac Vieux Desert Band. ]]></img>
  </marker>
  
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
    <caption name="Grand Traverse Band of Ottawa and Chippewa" src="181GrandTraverse.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.gtbindians.org"  > <![CDATA[In 1855, ancestors of the people in this community signed a treaty ceding land in return for a reservation.  They subsequently lost this land and gradually began buying land for their community.  In 1980, they obtained federal recognition as a tribe and by 1998 had a land base of almost 500 acres scattered in six counties. The tribe has about 4,100 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.567637" lng="-86.176880" />
	<pos lat="44.552116" lng="-86.094482" />
	<pos lat="44.505528" lng="-86.105469" />
	<pos lat="44.501644" lng="-86.182373" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Grand Traverse Band Service Area.  Photo courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan. ]]></img>
    </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ottawa" duplicate="yes">
    <caption name="Grand Traverse Band of Ottawa and Chippewa " src="181GrandTraverse.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0x003300" url="http://www.gtbindians.org"  > <![CDATA[In 1855, ancestors of the people in this community signed a treaty ceding land in return for a reservation.  They subsequently lost this land and gradually began buying land for their community.  In 1980, they obtained federal recognition as a tribe and by 1998 had a land base of almost 500 acres scattered in six counties. The tribe has about 4,100 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="44.567637" lng="-86.176880" />
	<pos lat="44.552116" lng="-86.094482" />
	<pos lat="44.505528" lng="-86.105469" />
	<pos lat="44.501644" lng="-86.182373" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Grand Traverse Band Service Area.  Photo courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan. ]]></img>
    </marker>
	
		<marker type="Ottawa">
	  <caption name="Little Traverse Bay Bands of Odawa Indians" src="197LittleTraverse.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0x003300" url="http://www.ltbbodawa-nsn.org"> <![CDATA[This Ottawa community obtained federal recognition in 1994 after many years of struggle. Today their land base is about 336 square miles, and the enrolled population of 4,200 lives in three communities.]]></caption>
		<pos lat="44.807578" lng="-85.516077" />
		<pos lat="44.809506" lng="-85.389734" />
		<pos lat="44.670505" lng="-85.400720" />
		<pos lat="44.678237" lng="-85.592981" />
		<pos lat="44.761281" lng="-85.595728" />
		<img><![CDATA[Little Traverse Bay Multi-County Tribal Service Area.  Map courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan.]]></img>
	  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Saginaw Chippewa Indian Tribe" src="179SaginawChippewa.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.sagchip.org"> <![CDATA[This tribe’s Isabella Indian Reservation was established by treaty in 1855. Much of the land was lost after allotment, but today the land base is about 1,400 acres. They have abut 3,400 members. The Saginaw Chippewa are the largest employer in the county. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="43.490362" lng="-85.754893" />
	<pos lat="43.470362" lng="-85.334180" />
	<pos lat="43.578641" lng="-85.332207" />
	<pos lat="43.562854" lng="-85.200933" />
	<pos lat="43.318446" lng="-85.202905" />
	<pos lat="43.338294" lng="-85.602070" />
	<pos lat="43.282704" lng="-85.602070" />
	<pos lat="43.290649" lng="-85.755879" /> 
	<img> <![CDATA[Saginaw Chippewa Multi-County Tribal Service Area.  Map courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan.]]></img>
  </marker>

  <marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians" src="196SaultSteMarieNEW.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.saulttribe.com" > <![CDATA[They ceded land and, in return, obtained reservation land in 1855, but after allotment these lands were lost.  The United States considered them part of the Bay Mills Indian Community, but they began to organize for independence in the 1950s, and in 1972 the federal government recognized them as an independent tribe.  In 1974, they bought land in several locations.  The enrolled population totals almost 32,000, and they are now the largest employer in northern Michigan. ]]></caption>
  	<pos lat="45.553157" lng="-84.979492" />
	<pos lat="45.545532" lng="-84.853149" />
	<pos lat="45.457769" lng="-84.831177" />
	<pos lat="45.465406" lng="-84.968506" />
	<img><![CDATA[Sault Ste. Marie Tribal Service Area.  Photo courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan. ]]></img>
  </marker>

  <marker type="Ojibwa">
  <caption name="Bay Mills Indian Community" src="192BayMills.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xff0000" url="http://www.baymills.org" > <![CDATA[This group of several villages of Ojibwa ceded land in return for reservation land in 1855. By 1861, the Bay Mills land included almost 800 acres. After the reservation lands were allotted, most of the land was lost, but at the time of the Indian Reorganization Act and, later, in the 1970s, the community began to acquire land.  Today, the reservation is almost 4,000 square miles and includes Sugar Island, a few miles east in St. Marys River.  Bay Mills has about 1,700 members.  In 1984 the community opened the first tribally owned casino in the United States.  This income helps support environmental protection, an extensive program for elders, and a tribal college.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.648380" lng="-85.215698" />
	<pos lat="45.652185" lng="-85.039917" />
	<pos lat="45.545532" lng="-85.056396" />
	<pos lat="45.545532" lng="-85.193726" />
	<img><![CDATA[Bay Mills Tribal Service Area.  Photo courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan. ]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Potawatomi">
  <caption name="Hannahville Indian Community " src="193Hannahville.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.hannahville.net" > <![CDATA[The people in this community are descendents of Potawatomi families who refused to leave Michigan.  In 1853, they were settled on Big Cedar River, where a Methodist missionary helped them locate on their own land.  In gratitude, they named their community after his wife, Hannah.  They organized under the Indian Reorganization Act in 1936.  Today they have just under 1,000 members and their reservation is about 8 square miles, with small parcels of scattered land amidst non-Indian holdings. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="45.434852" lng="-88.375269" />
	<pos lat="45.434852" lng="-88.243433" />
	<pos lat="45.362217" lng="-88.237939" />
	<pos lat="45.358392" lng="-88.369775" />
	<img><![CDATA[Hannahville Tribal Service Area.  Photo Courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan. ]]></img>
  </marker>
	
	<marker type="Potawatomi">
  <caption name="Match-E-Be-Nash-She-Wish Band of Pottawatomi Indians " src="143AMatchebenashshewishLogo.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.mbpi.org" > <![CDATA[This village of Gun Lake Potawatomi ceded land and, in return, received reservation land along with their Ottawa allies in the Treaty of 1855.  In the aftermath of a wave of immigration, in the 1840s they avoided removal by moving to an Episcopal mission, where they obtained a small land base in fee patent.  They could not pay the taxes on this land and lost it.  In 1999, they obtained recognition from the federal government as a tribe.  Their community is named after the first chief to contact non-Indians in 1795.  The tribe has about 350 members.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="43.046425" lng="-86.048291" />
	<pos lat="43.070309" lng="-85.762646" />
	<pos lat="42.926860" lng="-85.762646" />
	<pos lat="42.918881" lng="-86.059277" />
	<img> <![CDATA[Tribal Seal.  Photo courtesy of Match-E-Be-Nash-She-Wish Band of Pottawatomi.   ]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Potawatomi">
  <caption name="Nottawaseppi Huron Band of Potawatomi" src="199NottawaseppiHuron.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.nhbpi.com"> <![CDATA[ This community occupies the Pine Creek reservation of about 300 acres, much of which they purchased. They incorporated in 1970, and in 1995, they obtained federal recognition as a tribe. They have 800 members. After they were federally recognized, they began developing businesses and improving their lands. ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="42.107550" lng="-85.566016" />
	<pos lat="42.115636" lng="-85.248535" />
	<pos lat="41.872614" lng="-85.270508" />
	<pos lat="41.864497" lng="-85.533057" />
	<img><![CDATA[Huron Potawatomi Multi-County Tribal Service Area.  Map courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan.]]></img>
  </marker>

	<marker type="Potawatomi">
  <caption name="Pokagon Band of Potawatomi Indians" src="195Pokagon.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0xfeba04" url="http://www.pokagon.com"> <![CDATA[In the Treaty of 1833, they negotiated to remain in southwest Michigan, where they subsequently bought land near Dowagiac. In 1841, they were threatened with removal but successfully took their case to court. After years of struggle, they obtained federal recognition as a tribe in 1994. They purchased land, and today, they own about 4,700 acres in southwest Michigan and northeastern Indiana. Their membership is about 3,200.]]></caption>
	<pos lat="41.936796" lng="-86.711963" />
	<pos lat="41.944942" lng="-86.437305" />
	<pos lat="41.798148" lng="-86.481250" />
	<pos lat="41.789983" lng="-86.711963" />
	<img><![CDATA[Pokagon Multi-Country Tribal Service Area.  Map courtesy of Inter-Tribal Council of Michigan.]]></img>
  </marker>

	
	<marker type="Ottawa">
  <caption name="Little River Band of Ottawa Indians" src="146Little-River-Band.jpg" state="Michigan" color="0x003300" url="http://www.lrboi.com" > <![CDATA[This community descends from 9 villages of the Grand River Ottawa.  In 1855, they ceded land in order to obtain a reservation.  The land was lost but in 1994 they obtained federal recognition as a tribe.  Today the tribe has about 50,000 acres in several counties.  There are about 4,000 tribal members.  Their business income supports an extensive environmental protection program and many social services.  ]]></caption>
	<pos lat="43.800304" lng="-86.807744" />
	<pos lat="43.740695" lng="-86.799717" />
	<pos lat="43.724925" lng="-86.871416" />
	<img><![CDATA[Tribal seal.  The circle represents creation and the interconnectedness of all life.  The river represents the Manistee River but also the fact that the band is a “riverine” people, always living along the major river systems of western Michigan.  The nine feathers symbolize the nine bands and their chiefs, who signed the 1855 Treaty of Detroit.  The members of the band descend from these people and the seal honors them.  The four-color band signifies four directions, four seasons, four stages of life, and the four “races” (because the community is “multi-racial”).  The eagles symbolize male and female contributions to family and community.  ]]></img>
  </marker>
</markers>
